Guide to the Sir William Wiseman Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Sir William Wiseman papers
1916-1961
MS 666
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9.5
(22 boxes)
Papers pertaining to the period 1917-1919 and specifically to diplomatic relations between Britain and the U.S. during that period. Includes correspondence between Wiseman and Edward M. House; official telegrams of the British Foreign Office and of U.S. officials; British and American official and private memoranda on war matters and on problems of the Peace Conference; and reports and correspondence on Russia and on the Zionist movement. Important correspondents include: Gordon Auchincloss, Arthur James Balfour, Winston Churchill, Thomas G. Masaryk, Ignace Jan Paderewski, the Marquis of Reading, Cecil Spring-Rice and William Tyrrell.
Wiseman, William, Sir, 1885-
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Sir William Wiseman in 1922 and Lady Joan Wiseman in 1966.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. World War I and the Paris Peace Conference. II. World War II. III. Business and Personal.
Scope and Contents
Sir William George Eden Wiseman, diplomat and liaison between the British government and the Wilson administration, is a figure of particular importance for the student of British-American relations during World War I.
The particular value of the William Wiseman Papers is the light they throw on Wiseman's role in the war. Incorporating correspondence from many prime movers of the British and American governments, Foreign Office memoranda, and a wealth of other materials, the Wiseman Papers thus offer significant resources for the study of World War I and the Paris Peace Conference. Their value is further enhanced by such closely related Yale collections as the Edward M. House Papers (MS 466), the Charles Seymour Papers (MS 441), and the Arthur Willert Papers (MS 720). The Papers also provide information on Wiseman's activities during World War II and his post-war career in investment banking. Wiseman's continuing interest in Anglo-American cooperation is a unifying theme throughout the entire collection.
Yale acquired the Wiseman Papers through two donations, the bulk of the World War I material (amounting to approximately half of the entire collection) as a gift from Sir William Wiseman in 1922, and the remainder from his wife in 1966. The later gift included several files of British military intelligence papers and other material from the First World War which Wiseman had withheld in 1922, World War II material, and business papers of the post-war period.
Although the 1922 donation, which comprises files kept by Wiseman in New York during the war, was heavily used by Charles Seymour in preparing his Intimate Papers of Colonel House and by other scholars, it had not received full arrangement and description by 1966. Further, a new system of organization was required in order to integrate the 1966 donation. In the new arrangement the World War I papers have largely remained under their former headings except for several catch-all categories which have been further sorted and clarified; some correspondence has been moved from subject files to the correspondence section.
The Wiseman Papers are now divided into three series: WORLD WAR I AND THE PARIS PEACE CONFERENCE, WORLD WAR II, and BUSINESS AND PERSONAL.
Series I, the largest and most important segment of the papers, is composed of two sections, "Select Correspondence" and "Subject Files," each arranged alphabetically. Represented in "Select Correspondence" are many British and American government officials and diplomats, as well as other European leaders. Among the most notable are Arthur James Balfour, Bernard M. Baruch, Louis D. Brandeis, Robert Cecil, Edward M. House, Thomas G. Masaryk, Arthur Murray (later Lord Elibank), Lord Northcliffe, Ignace Jan Pederewski, Lord Eustace Percy, and Lord Reading.
The "Subject Files" section contains memoranda, printed matter, and a large number of Foreign Office cables, many but not all of which are duplicated in "Select Correspondence"; some cables and other communiques are found only in "Subject Files." Cross-references are provided only to original letters located in "Subject Files."
Almost half of "Subject Files" is devoted to the Paris Peace Conference of 1919; the contents include a short diary kept by Wiseman from January 17 to February 17, 1919 (folders 178-179) and daily bulletins and other printed matter of the British delegation to the conference, as well as memoranda on a variety of topics discussed at the conference. Another area of special interest is Wiseman's file on Russia, which incorporates a lengthy series of cables and memoranda discussing Allied intervention in Russia in 1917-1918 (folders 225-254) and material on propaganda and intelligence gathering in Russia (folders 255-264). Included is a small amount of correspondence from W. Somerset Maugham and Emanuel V. Voska. Also of particular interest in "Subject Files" are papers from Wiseman's military intelligence work in the United States.
His office was charged with protecting munitions and other British supplies and investigating people suspected of anti-British activities. The files include organizational and financial papers from the New York office and reports from various agents; see folders 159-177. See also the correspondence of Manuel del Campo (folders 17-19) and Norman Thwaites (folders 84-85).
Completing Series I is a detailed card-file subject index (Box 12), compiled under Charles Seymour's tenure as curator of the House Collection. Although box and folder references in this index can no longer be cited in calling for material, the index is still a useful guide since most of the indexed material is filed under the old subject headings.
Series II, WORLD WAR II, is quite small and offers but an incomplete record of Wiseman's intelligence and war-relief activities. Included are correspondence dealing with intelligence matters (folders 4, 12), memoranda and correspondence of the Petroleum (Warfare) Department (folder 9) and Union Jack Clubs (folder 11), and memoranda on such subjects as Anglo-American relations. The material are arranged alphabetically by topic.
In Series III, business and financial papers stemming from Wiseman's partnership with Kuhn, Loeb, and Company make up the bulk of the first two sections ("Select Correspondence" and "General Correspondence," both arranged alphabetically). Wiseman was active in promoting capital investment in underdeveloped countries (e.g. folders 24, 61-64, 79) and exploration and utilization of natural resources, especially energy sources. It was these interests which led to Wiseman's dealings with Caloust Gulbenkian, the multi-millionaire financier and pioneer of petroleum development in the Middle East. Other correspondence in these sections relates to corporations of which Wiseman was an executive (for instance, the United States Rubber Company and Industria Electrica) and of which he was a major stockholder (like Photocolor Process Corporation). The material in these two sections have for the most part been left in the arrangement used by Wiseman's office, with the result that papers relating to a given corporation may include material from correspondents who appear in numerous other files as well, particularly business associates such as John Guest, John Schiff, and Siegmund Warburg.
These two sections also contain papers relating to Wiseman's continuing interest in Anglo-American relations and his philanthropic endeavors; correspondence with Charles Seymour and Lord Reading concerning their books about the First World War, as well as with others studying that period; and a few letters from prominent figures such as Dwight Eisenhower, Adlai Stevenson, and Harry Truman. There is also some correspondence from people with whom Wiseman worked during the world wars, including Arthur Murray (Lord Elibank), W. Somerset Maugham, and others. There is little of a personal nature outside of a few letters from friends and from Wiseman's three daughters, Rosemary Hulton, Margaret Rainsford-Hannay, and Sheila Wiseman.
The third section of Series III, "Other Papers," contains a miscellany of writings by Wiseman, personal financial papers, memorabilia, several photographs, and biographical material.
Biographical / Historical
Sir William Wiseman (1885-1962): international banker working at Herndon's in London before World War I; during World War I served in the infantry as a lieutenant colonel, then in military intelligence; acted as liaison between British government and Wilson, and as advisor at the Paris Peace Conference; after World War I joined banking firm of Kuhn, Loeb & Co. in New York.
Business; Developing countries -- Finance; World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1939-1945; Zionism; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- United States; New York (State); Soviet Union; United States -- Foreign relations -- 1913-1921; United States -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain; Bankers; Diplomats; Percy of Newcastle, Eustace Percy, Baron, 1887-1958; Ackerman, Carl W. (Carl William), 1890-1970; Amery, L. S. (Leopold Stennett), 1873-1955; Ascherson, Charles Stephen, d. 1945; Auchincloss, Gordon, 1886-1943; Baldwin, Stanley Baldwin, Earl, 1867-1947; Balfour, Arthur James, 1848-1930; Barclay, Colville; Baruch, Bernard M. (Bernard Mannes), 1870-1965; Beck, James M. (James Montgomery), 1861-1936; Beer, George Louis, 1872-1920; Blackwood, A. T.; Blythe, Howell; Brandeis, Louis Dembitz, 1856-1941; Brown, Frederick Walworth, b. 1875; Buckler, W. H. (William Hepburn), 1867-1952; Caird, Andrew; Campo, Manuel Marʹia del; Cecil of Chelwood, Robert Gascoyne-Cecil, Viscount, 1864-1958; Churchill, Clementine, 1885-1977; Churchill, Winston, 1874-1965; Coffin, Charles A. (Charles Albert), 1844-1926; Craufurd-Stuart, C. K.; Cunliffe-Owen, Philip Frederick, 1855-1926; Curtis, Lionel, 1872-1955; De Haas, Jacob, 1872-1937; Drummond, Eric, Sir, 1876-1951; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965; Frazier, Arthur Hugh, 1868-; Gaselee, S. (Stephen), 1882-1943; Gaunt, Guy, Sir, 1869-1953; Gottheil, Richard J. H. (Richard James Horatio), 1862-1936; Granville-Barker, Harley, 1877-1946; Gulbenkian, Calouste Sarkis, 1869-1955; House, Edward Mandell, 1858-1938; Hudson, Robert Arundell, 1864-1927; Johen, R. Waley; Knowlton, Hugh, 1893-; Koukal, Alois B.; Lewis, James, 1863-1939; Lindsay, Ronald Charles, Sir, 1877-1945; Lloyd, G. E. R. (Geoffrey Ernest Richard), 1933-; Long, Walter Hume Long, Viscount, 1854-1924; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875; Mack, Julian W. (Julian William), 1866-1943; Malcolm, Zachary, Sir, 1868-; Marquand, John P. (John Phillips), 1893-1960; Masaryk, T. G. (Tomáš Garrigue), 1850-1937; Maugham, W. Somerset (William Somerset), 1874-1965; Miller, David Hunter, 1875-1961; Montgomery, Hubert; Murray, Arthur Cecil, 3rd viscount, 1879-; Nicolson, Harold, 1886-1968; Northcliffe, Alfred Harmsworth, Viscount, 1865-1922; Oakes, Eunice; Paderewski, Ignace Jan, 1860-1941; Philips, Charles Joseph, 1880-1933; Plunkett, Horace Curzon, Sir, 1854-1932; Rainsford-Hannay, Margaret Wiseman; Rainsford-Hannay, Ramsay; Reading, Gerald Rufus Isaacs, Marquess of, 1889-1960; Riddell, George Allardice Riddell, Baron, 1865-1934; Schiff, John Mortimer; Seymour, Charles, 1885-1963; Spring Rice, Cecil, Sir, 1859-1918; Stamfordham, Arthur John Bigge, Baron, 1849-1931; Standing, Guy, 1948-; Stephenson, William Samuel, 1896-1989; Storey, Eustace; Strauss, Lewis Lichtenstein, 1896-1974; Strode-Jackson, Arnold N. S.; Thwaites, Norman Graham, 1872-; Tyrrell, William, Sir; Willert, Arthur, Sir, 1882-1973; Wilson, Fred J.; Wiseman, William, Sir, 1885-; Wovschin, William Alex; Kuhn, Loeb & Company; Paris Peace Conference ( 1919-1920)
- WORLD WAR I AND THE PARIS PEACE CONFERENCE, 1915-1926; Series I; 5; (12 boxes)
  - Select Correspondence
    - Ackerman, Carl W., 1918 February - September (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Alston, _____, 1918 September - October (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Amery, L.S.
      General
      See: box 5, folder 126
    - Ascherson, Charles S., (*), 1917-1918, 1919 July (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
    - Auchincloss, Gordon
      See: box 6, folder 152
    - Balfour, Arthur James, (*), 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 6-11)
    - Barclay, Colville, (*), 1918 July - October (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - Baruch, Bernard M., 1919 May 26 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Beck, James M., 1918 August 9 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Beer, G. Louis, 1918 September (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Blackwood, A.T.
      See: box 6, folder 173
    - Blythe, Howell, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Brandeis, Louis D., 1918 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Bridge, ____, 1917 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Browning, Fred W.
      See: box 6, folder 159
    - Buckler, William H., 1918 February - March (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Caird, Andrew, 1917 September - October (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Cecil, Robert, 1917 August - 1919 March (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Churchill, Winston, 1917 July - October (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Coffin, C.A., 1918 July 8 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Craufurd-Stuart, C.K., 1918 March - April (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Cunliffe Owen, Frederick, 1918 December (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Curtis, L.
      See: box 6, folder 149
    - De Haas, Jacob
      See: box 11, folders 278-282
    - del Campo, Manuel M., (*), 1918 - 1919 May (Box 1, Folder 17-19)
    - Drummond, Eric, (*), 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 20-27)
      See also: box 5, folder 138
      See also: box 6, folder 152
      See also: box 10, folder 256
    - Frankfurter, Felix
      See: box 11, folder 282
    - Frazier, Arthur Hugh, 1917 Dec, 1918 May (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Gaselee, Stephen
      See: box 9, folder 205
    - Gaunt, Sir Guy R.
      See: box 6, folders 166-171
    - Gottheil, Richard
      See: box 10, folders 255-256
      See: box 11, folders 277-278
    - Granville-Barker, Harley
      See: box 6, folders 161-165
    - House, Edward M., (*), 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 29-31)
    - Hudson, Robert Arundell, 1917 August - October (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Johen (?), R. Waley, 1917 October 19 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Koukal, Alois B.
      See: box 10, folder 262
    - Lewis, James Hamilton, 1918 July 26 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Lindsay, R.C., 1919 June - July (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Long, Walter, 1917 September 15 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Lyell, Charles, 1918 September 6 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Mack, Julian W.
    - Malcolm, Ian, 1919 July - Sep, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Marquand, John Phillips, 1918 November 8 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Masaryk, Thomas G., 1918 July - October (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Maugham, W. Somerset
      See: box 10, folder 256
    - Miller, David Hunter, 1917 October - 1918 September (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Montgomery, Hubert, 1918 June 11 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      See also: box 5, folder 133
    - Murray, Arthur, (*), 1917 September - 1919 (Box 2, Folder 36-54)
      See also: box 5, folders 120-121
      See also: box 5, folder 126
      See also: box 5, folder 135
      See also: box 10, folder 244
      See also: box 14, folder 18-22
    - Nicholson, Harold, 1919 March 15 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Northcliffe, Alfred C.W. Harmsworth, (*), 1917 June - 1918 (Box 3, Folder 56-63)
    - Paderewski, Ignace Jan, (*), 1917 September - 1919 April (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Percy of Newcastle, Eustace Percy, (*), 1918 March - September (Box 3, Folder 65-66)
    - Phillips, C.J., (*), 1917 - 1918 January (Box 3, Folder 67-69)
    - Plunkett, Horace
      See: box 5, folder 138
    - Reading, Gerald R. Isaacs (Marquis of) (*), 1917 September - 1919 July (Box 3, Folder 70-80)
    - Riddell, George
    - Spring-Rice, Cecil, (*), 1916 - 1918 Feb, 1926 August 18 (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Stamfordham, Arthur Biggs, 1918 March - 1919 August (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Standing, Guy, 1917 January 13, 1918 January 28 (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Strode-Jackson, A., 1919 April 3 (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Stuart, _____, 1919 May (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Thwaites, Norman G., (*), 1918 March - 1919 April (Box 3, Folder 84-85)
      See also: box 6, folder 174
      See also: box 9, folder 212
    - Tyrrell, William, (*), 1919 July - September (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Willert, Arthur, 1917 Nov, 1918 January (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Wilson, Fred J.
      See: box 5, folder 136
    - The World, 1918 February - June (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Wovschin, William Alex.
      See: box 11, folder 277
  - Subject Files
    - Alsace-Lorraine, 1917-1918 (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - American Mission (1917 Nov), 1917 October - 1918 Jan, undated (Box 4, Folder 89-90)
    - American participation in the war, 1916 December - 1918 October (Box 4, Folder 91-108)
    - Anglo-American relations, 1917 April - 1919 Mar, 1921 May (Box 4, Folder 109-110)
    - Austria-Hungary, 1917-f1919 February (Box 4, Folder 111-113)
    - The Balkans, 1916, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 114)
    - "The Baltic Provinces" (memorandum), 1918 May 17 (Box 5, Folder 115)
    - Bulgaria, 1918 May - Oct, undated (Box 5, Folder 116-118)
    - Conference of Oppressed Nationalities, 1918 October (Box 5, Folder 119)
    - Economic policies of the Allies, 1917-1918 (Box 5, Folder 120-121)
    - Europe, conditions in, 1917 August - December (Box 5, Folder 122-123)
    - Finland, 1918 February - August (Box 5, Folder 124)
    - Freedom of the seas, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 125)
    - German colonies, 1917-1918 (Box 5, Folder 126)
    - German war aims, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 127-128)
    - Germany, 1917 - 1919 March (Box 5, Folder 129-131)
    - Greco-Italian relations, 1918 August - September (Box 5, Folder 132)
    - Hearst, William Randolph, and the International News Service, 1916-1918 (Box 5, Folder 133-136)
    - The Inquiry: "Report of Progress to January 15, 1918,", 1918 January 15 (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - Irish Home Rule Convention, 1917-1919, undated (Box 5, Folder 138-139)
    - Irish question, 1916-1918 (Box 5, Folder 140-142)
    - Japan, 1918 September 16, undated (Box 6, Folder 143)
    - Joint Blockade Council, 1917 August - October (Box 6, Folder 144)
    - Latin America, 1917-1918 (Box 6, Folder 145)
    - League of Nations, 1917-1919, undated (Box 6, Folder 146-154)
    - Lloyd George, David: speeches, 1916-1917 (Box 6, Folder 155)
    - Mexico, 1917 - 1919 Jan, undated (Box 6, Folder 156-158)
    - Military intelligence
      - Activities in the U.S., 1916-1919 (Box 6, Folder 159-176)
      - New York financial records, 1916 Nov, 1918 January - October (Box 6, Folder 177)
    - Peace Conference
      - Diary of Sir William Wiseman, 1919 January 17 - February 7 (Box 7, Folder 178-179)
      - British delegation
        - Daily Bulletin, 1919 January 18 - March 24 (Box 7, Folder 180-190)
        - Daily Bulletin, 1919 March 25 - May 2 (Box 8, Folder 191-197)
        - Daily Bulletin Supplement, [1919 Mar] (Box 8, Folder 198)
        - Printed matter, memoranda, other papers, 1918 October - 1919 March (Box 8, Folder 199)
      - Cables, 1918 December - 1919 July (Box 8, Folder 200-203)
      - Egypt: U.S. recognition of British Protectorate, 1919 April (Box 9, Folder 204)
      - Films, 1919 February - April (Box 9, Folder 205)
      - Fiume, 1919 January 21 (Box 9, Folder 206)
      - German colonies, 1919 January (Box 9, Folder 207)
      - Indemnities and reparations, 1918 December - 1919 May, undated (Box 9, Folder 208-209)
      - Liberia, 1919 March 5 (Box 9, Folder 210)
      - Russia, 1919 March - April (Box 9, Folder 211)
      - Syria, 1919 January (Box 9, Folder 212)
      - United States
        - Attitude towards the Peace Conference and ratification, [ca. 1918 October 20], 1919 (Box 9, Folder 213)
        - War aims and peace terms, 1918 October - 1919 March (Box 9, Folder 214-216)
      - Miscellaneous, 1918-1919 (Box 9, Folder 217)
    - Persia, 1918 August - September (Box 9, Folder 218)
    - Poland, 1917 May - 1919 April (Box 9, Folder 219-222)
    - Propaganda and intelligence work, proposals for, 1917-1918 (Box 9, Folder 223)
    - Russell, Bertrand, 1918 March 23 (Box 9, Folder 224)
    - Russia
      - Allied intervention, 1917 - 1918 July 10 (Box 9, Folder 225-241)
      - Allied intervention, 1918 July 11 - December (Box 10, Folder 242-254)
      - Intelligence and propaganda, 1917 April - 1918 September (Box 10, Folder 255-264)
    - Schleswig-Holstein: memorandum, 1918 October 27 (Box 10, Folder 265)
    - Supreme War Council and Inter-Allied Council, 1917 September - 1918 August (Box 10, Folder 266-269)
    - Treaties, Secret wartime: copies of texts, 1915-1917 (Box 10, Folder 270-272)
    - "Turkey in Europe and Asia" (memorandum), 1917 October 22 (Box 10, Folder 273)
    - War aims and peace terms, 1917-1918 (Box 11, Folder 274-276)
    - Zionism, 1917 April - 1918 (Box 11, Folder 277-282)
    - Card file index (Box 12)
- WORLD WAR II, 1938-1948; Series II; 0.25; (1 box)
  - Anglo-American relations, 1940-1943, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - British War Relief Society, [1941 Jun?] (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Czechoslovakia, 1946 July 1 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Drought, James M.: correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Guest, John S.: "Britain and the Future,", 1947 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Japan, 1941, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Latin America, 1941, 1943 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Lothian, Philip H. Kerr: correspondence, 1939-1940 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Petroleum (Warfare) Department, 1943-1945 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Russia, 1943 September 21 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Union Jack Clubs: correspondence, 1941-1946 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Wiedemann, Fritz: correspondence and reports, 1940-1948 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous printed matter, 1938-1941 (Box 13, Folder 13)
- BUSINESS AND PERSONAL, 1917-1961; Series III; 3.25 linear feet (8 boxes)
  - Select Correspondence
    - Allen & Overy, (*), 1956-1961 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - American Cyanamid Company, (*), 1935-1938 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Ascherson, Mrs. Charles S., (*), 1948-1961 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Auchincloss, Mr. and Mrs. Gordon, 1918-1928, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Baldwin, Stanley, 1939 May 4 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - British Book Centre, Inc., (*), 1950-1951 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Brown, G. Phillpotts, (*), 1950-1956 (Box 14, Folder 6-7)
    - Canadian businesses, (*), 1946-1959 (Box 14, Folder 8-10)
    - Caribbean Cement Company, (*), 1957-1958 (Box 14, Folder 11-13)
    - Churchill, Lady Clementine S. (*)
      See: box 18, folders 117-118
    - Churchill, Winston, (*), 1953 January 10 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Courtaulds, Ltd., 1948-1951 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Dollar Exports Advisory Council, (*), 1951-1953 (Box 14, Folder 15-16)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight David, 1950 February - March (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Elibank, Arthur Murray (Viscount of), (* ), 1945-1959 (Box 14, Folder 18-22)
      See also: box 2, folders 36-54
    - Gaunt, Sir Guy, 1949, undated (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Getty, J. Paul, 1959 July (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Ghana bauxite project, (*), 1957 May - July (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - Gulbenkian, Caloust Sarkis, (*), 1944-1958, undated (Box 15, Folder 25-51)
    - Hammerstein, Oscar, 2nd, 1958 May (Box 15, Folder 52)
    - Hohenlohe, Prince Max de, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 52)
    - Horodyski, Count Jan, 1947-1948 (Box 15, Folder 52)
    - House, Edward M., 1932-1933, undated (Box 15, Folder 52)
    - Hughes-Owens Company, (*), 1950-1951 (Box 15, Folder 53)
    - Hulton, Frederick and Rosemary (Wiseman), 1955-1959 (Box 15, Folder 54)
    - Industria Eléctrica de México, (* ), 1946-1958 (Box 16, Folder 55-59)
    - Intercontinental Exchange, Inc., (*), 1957-1960 (Box 16, Folder 60)
    - Jamaican government loans, (*), 1957-1960 (Box 16, Folder 61-64)
    - Justa Petroleum Corporation, 1937-1941 (Box 16, Folder 65)